☆独家制作☆
喜马拉雅主播 & 微信公众号:
美国青少年英语
仅供交流学习  禁止商用盈利
地球脉动III
Beneath the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico...
在墨西哥尤卡坦半岛之下
..lies another world.
有一片别样的世界
A labyrinth of caves...
迷宫般的洞穴
..carved by freshwater...
由淡水雕刻而成
..and essential for life on Earth.
淡水对地球上的生命至关重要
Freshwater shapes the land and the creatures that live in it...
淡水塑造了大地 塑造了其中的万千生命
..in the most surprising ways.
以最令人惊讶的方式
淡水
The rainforest of Costa Rica.
哥斯达黎加的雨林
As you might expect, it rains most days.
不难想见 这里大部分时间都在下雨
But it's only during the wet season
但只有在雨季时
that the rains become torrential.
才会有如此倾盆大雨
And with them...
伴随着滂沱的大雨
..comes a most remarkable creature.
一种非凡无比的生物出现了
Gliding tree frogs.
滑翔树蛙
Thousands drop in...
成千上万只树蛙涌来
..to gather at this newly-formed pond.
聚集在这片新形成的池塘中
They all have an urgent need.
它们无不有着迫切的需要
To breed.
繁殖
This female needs to find a leaf
雌性树蛙需要找一片树叶
and lay her eggs.
从而在其上产卵
The breeding frenzy will only last one day...
这场繁殖的热潮只将持续一天
..so she needs to get a move on.
因此它得抓紧时间了
There are lots of eager males.
盼望得到垂青的雄性树蛙有很多
Nine for every female.
九名候选者竞争一个席位
And all are ready to spring into action.
全都蓄势待发
So, for her, getting a partner is no problem.
因此对于雌性树蛙来说 寻求伴侣不成问题
But the other males are desperate.
但失败者决定孤注一掷
For this female, mating is rather chaotic.
对于雌性树蛙来说 求爱过程相当混乱
Things are getting out of hand.
事情有些失控了
There is one way to deal with this.
有一种解决方法
A few well-placed kicks...
踹它们几脚
..usually does the job.
往往卓有成效
Problem solved.
问题解决了
She and her partner can now finally mate...
现在雌性树蛙终于可以与伴侣结合
..in relative peace.
在一片相对平静的环境下
The eggs are positioned perfectly...
树蛙产卵的位置
..directly overhanging the pond.
恰好位于池塘正上方
This is the ideal nursery for tadpoles.
这里是理想的蝌蚪育婴室
For now, her work here is done.
如今 雌性树蛙的工作已经完成
She'll be back next year when the heavy rains return.
它将在明年大雨时分如期归来
As quickly as freshwater appears...
淡水的出现
..it can vanish.
有时稍纵即逝
Southeast Sri Lanka.
斯里兰卡东南部
It's the middle of the dry season.
正当旱季中期
This is the only remaining water hole for miles around.
方圆数里内 这是唯一一处水坑
Mugger crocodiles -
沼泽鳄
giants, five metres long.
长达五米的巨型鳄鱼
Dozens are hiding...
十数只沼泽鳄
..beneath the surface.
潜藏于水面之下
And others...
还有更多鳄鱼
..are on their way.
将来到此处
This male has been travelling for hours.
这只雄性鳄鱼已经奔波了数小时
The water hole is the only place where he has a chance
这片水坑是它唯一有机会
to catch a deer.
捕食鹿的地方
A single adult would be enough to feed him for the entire dry season.
只需捕食一只成年鹿 便足够沼泽鳄度过整个旱季
But hunting prey that knows you're here...
但猎物也已知晓敌人环伺在周围
..requires something truly remarkable.
想要捕捉成功 就需要一些奇招
He creates...
沼泽鳄布置了
..a trap.
一个陷阱
He digs down into the mud...
它往泥里深挖
..deep enough to hide beneath the vegetation.
直到身形被植被隐藏
Perfect camouflage.
完美的伪装
He has built his trap right on the water's edge...
沼泽鳄将陷阱布置在水边
..so it's the first place that thirsty deer will come to drink.
这里正是前来饮水的鹿的必经之处
These crocodiles have learned to exploit
这些鳄鱼已经学会了如何利用
the deer's desperate need for freshwater.
鹿对于淡水的迫切需求
Freshwater transforms not only the lives of animals...
淡水不仅改变了动物的生命轨迹
..but entire landscapes.
还改变了整片地貌
Every year, over a trillion litres of water
每年 超过一万亿升水
flow into the Kalahari Desert.
流入卡拉哈里沙漠
It has travelled a thousand miles from where it fell as rain.
水流自降雨地流到此处已经穿越了近两千公里
And on arrival...
水流的到来
..it turns the Kalahari...
将卡拉哈里沙漠
..into a vast oasis.
变成了一片绿洲
The Okavango Delta.
奥卡万戈三角洲
These waters attract millions of animals.
淡水吸引着数以百万计的动物
And for some, now is the perfect time to raise a family.
对于一些动物来说 现在是组建家庭的绝佳时机
A lily-trotter.
长脚水雉
And he is a father on duty.
它也是一名尽责的父亲
He has not just one...
雄性水雉养育着不止一只
..but four newly-hatched chicks.
而是多达四只刚孵化的孩子
They won't be able to fly for another six weeks...
雏鸟六周后才能飞行
..so, until then, he alone is their protector.
因此在那之前 只有成年雄性水雉才能保护它们
Walking on water is not straightforward...
水上行走并非易事
..so he must show them how to be a lily-trotter.
因此雄性水雉要教雏鸟如何在睡莲上行走
The floodwaters make the perfect training ground.
高涨的水位使这里成为了绝佳的训练场
And in two weeks...
两周后
..his chicks not only double in size...
雏鸟不仅个头长大了一倍
..they grow in confidence.
信心也增加了一倍
But this is a dangerous place to stray.
但这里其实危机四伏
He sounds the alarm,
雄性水雉发出警报
and his chicks instantly freeze.
雏鸟便立刻停了下来
They can't yet fly to safety.
可它们还无法飞离险地
But there is one thing he can do to protect them.
但雄性水雉还有一种手段来保护雏鸟
And it's risky.
一种风险极高的手段
Get close enough to distract...
靠近鳄鱼以分散它的注意力
..and hopefully divert the crocodile.
试图将其引开
Mission accomplished.
大功告成
He signals the all clear.
雄性水雉示意警报解除
But one chick is missing.
然而却少了一只雏鸟
His calls...
雄性水雉的呼唤
..go unanswered.
没有得到回应
A little bedraggled but alive and well.
有些蓬头垢面 但好在没丢掉性命
His chick just hadn't heard his call.
这只雏鸟只是没有听到父亲的呼唤而已
And when danger threatens,
危险来临时
its always better to be safe than sorry.
小心驶得万年船
He's brought his chicks, all four of them,
四只雏鸟在父亲的呵护下
to the verge of independence.
逐步迈向了独立的新生活
Whilst lily-trotters are well adapted
虽然长脚水雉很好地适应了
to life in this flooded world...
这片被洪水淹没的世界
..these residents of the delta are not.
三角洲的另一批居民却还没有适应
African painted dogs.
非洲野犬
Normally, they are remarkably successful hunters.
通常情况下 它们是极成功的猎手
But this pack of five hasn't eaten in days.
但这五只野犬已经好几天没吃过东西了
Finding prey isn't the problem.
寻找猎物并不是问题
This herd of lechwe is only a few hundred metres away.
驴羚群就在数百米远处
But between them is deep water.
但深不见底的水流挡住了去路
It's not safe to cross here.
从这里跨过去太危险了
On dry land, the dogs can run at over 40mph.
在陆地上 非洲野犬能以每小时60公里以上的速度奔驰
But when threatened, lechwe always seek the safety of water.
但当驴羚遇到危险时 总是借助水域保护自己
With their splayed hooves and long hind legs,
它们有着分叉的蹄子和长长的后腿
they can power their way through the water.
能够在水中大步向前
The dogs can't.
非洲野犬却不行
The pack won't be able to outswim the lechwe.
非洲野犬虽然水性略逊
But they do have a strategy.
但它们有一种策略
The dogs drive the lechwe to where they have the advantage.
非洲野犬将驴羚赶向自己的主场
Back towards dry land.
赶回陆地
Now the pack can regain lost ground.
现在 野犬夺回了优势
Success today, but tomorrow the pack will need to hunt again.
今天是成功了 但明天能否继续成功还是未知数
In the Okavango,
在奥卡万戈三角洲
animals must always adapt to the coming and going of freshwater.
动物必须适应这里时有时无的淡水
But there are a few rare places, as here in Lake Malawi,
但在一些罕见之处 比如马拉维湖
where freshwater has lain for millions of years.
淡水数百万年不间断的存在
And that has enabled life to evolve
这使生命得以进化
into a dazzling diversity of species.
形成了此处千姿百态的丰富物种
There are over a thousand different kinds of fish here...
这里孕育着数以千计不同的鱼类
..more than any other lake on Earth.
比地球上任何一处湖泊都多
Competition in these waters is intense.
水中各色物种的竞争激烈异常
Meet Nimbochromis livingstonii.
这是利氏雨丽鱼 也称迷彩鲷
A master of deception
一名骗术高手
that tricks other fish into thinking it's dead.
假装自己已经死了
Its mottled colouration mimics decaying flesh.
迷彩鲷身上斑驳的色彩看上去如同腐烂的肉体
But to appear dead...
但想要装死
..one must at least...
迷彩鲷必须
..act dead.
如尸体般一动不动
This juvenile is fooling no-one.
这条年轻的迷彩鲷骗不到任何鱼
Perhaps faking his death will be more believable.
也许假装猝死会更可信
Blown it.
搞砸了
A more subtle performance will be needed.
演技还需进一步打磨
This is more convincing.
这次更逼真了
But his aim must be better than that.
但显然还需要继续提高
Nearly.
就差一点
It seems he's overstayed his welcome.
看来得换一个地方了
In a final effort...
最后一次尝试
..he appears to even hold his breath.
迷彩鲷似乎甚至屏住了呼吸
Success at last.
终于成功了
All it took was a million years of evolution...
这一切需要生物百万年来的演化
..and the unique stability of this ancient lake.
以及这片湖泊历久弥坚的稳定性
Off the western coast of Equatorial Africa
赤道非洲的西海岸外
lies the volcanic island of Bioko.
坐落着比奥科火山岛
Freshwater here has a turbulent nature.
这里的淡水十分汹涌
Few venture into such waters,
很少有生命敢于冒险入水
but for those that do, there can be great rewards.
但风险越高 收益越高
After months feeding and growing out at sea,
经过几个月的海中觅食与生长
these gobies are ready to breed.
这些虾虎鱼已经做好了繁殖的准备
And the safest place to lay their eggs
最安全的产卵处
is somewhere that ocean predators can't reach.
是海洋捕食者无法染指的地方
The top of this waterfall.
这座瀑布顶端
Surely an impossible journey for a fish.
对鱼来说 无疑是一处不可能的目的地
But over the coming days, the gobies transform themselves.
但在接下来的几天里 虾虎鱼会改变自己
They change colour.
颜色发生变化
Their mouth rotates and acts like a kind of suction cup...
嘴部转动 如同一个吸盘
..which they will certainly need.
这正是它们需要的
Because the only way...is up.
华山一条路 它们必须登上顶端
It is 30 metres to the top.
垂直落差高达30米
They are only an inch long.
而虾虎鱼身长只有不到3厘米
This is the equivalent of a human being scaling a waterfall
相当于人类去攀登
over a mile high.
近两公里高的瀑布
Millions attempt the climb...
数以百万计的虾虎鱼向顶端进发
..but less than 1% will make it.
但只有不到1%能成功登顶
This goby has been climbing for days.
这只虾虎鱼已经爬了好几天了
Made it!
成功了
Those that reach the top can now prepare to breed.
抵达瀑布顶端的虾虎鱼现在可以准备繁殖了
And when the time comes, their young will be washed back out to sea.
时机成熟时 虾虎鱼幼崽将被湍流冲回大海
The extraordinary power of flowing water
流水的非凡力量
makes it our planet's greatest architect.
使其成为地球上最伟大的建筑师
This may look like the surface of an alien planet...
这里的地表看上去仿佛如同外星世界
..but these strange patterns are channels of freshwater...
但这些奇异的图案实际上是通往海洋的
..flowing towards the sea.
一条条淡水河道
For 3.8 billion years,
38亿年来
ever since the first rains fell...
自从第一滴雨水洒落大地
..freshwater has been making this journey.
淡水便无休止的循环往复
But today, two thirds of our world's great rivers
然而今天 世界上三分之二的大江大河
no longer reach the sea.
已不再入海
There is a finite amount of freshwater on Earth...
地球上淡水资源有限
..so humans have devised extraordinary means
因此人类设计了非凡的方法
to ensure that it is always available to meet our every demand.
来确保有足够淡水满足我们的需求
We now control freshwater...
我们如今大规模地
..on a colossal scale.
控制淡水资源
The largest irrigation system on Earth
地球上最大的灌溉系统
has been built here in Pakistan.
建于巴基斯坦
A vast network of dams and canals...
这是一个由水坝和运河组成的巨大网络
..that diverts and drains the great Indus River.
从而从印度河中引水配水
It's used to irrigate an area the size of England.
整个系统被用来灌溉一片英国大小的区域
This man-made freshwater world
这片人造淡水世界
provides water and a livelihood
为数百万人
for millions of people...
提供了水资源和生计
..but at a cost to the natural world.
但这是以自然世界的损害为代价的
A rare creature has become stranded in this irrigation canal.
一种稀有的生物被困于灌溉渠中
And the water will soon be gone,
渠中的水很快就将消失
used to supply the surrounding land.
以供应周围土地的需要
Endangered, they number fewer than 2,000 individuals.
这种生物濒临灭绝 数量不足2000只
An Indus river dolphin.
印度河豚
This female dolphin is 150 miles from the main river.
这只雌性印度河豚的位置距离干流240公里
She can't return on her own,
它无法靠自己的力量回去
so the only option is for this rescue team to take her.
因此唯一的选择就是由救援队救走它
Out of water, she cannot survive for long.
离开水 印度河豚无法生存太久
The journey back to the river will take hours.
回到河流的路途将花费数小时
Her life now depends on these people.
它的生命如今只能指望救援队
Nearly 30 dolphins had to be rescued in one month alone.
仅一个月便有近30只印度河豚陷入危险 不得不依靠救援
Freshwater is not only a resource for humans.
淡水不仅是人类的资源
It is the home for countless species
更是无数物种的家园
that simply cannot survive without it.
没有淡水 便无法生存
Freshwater is the lifeblood of Planet Earth.
淡水是地球的命脉
幕后花絮
To film the story of the most endangered freshwater dolphin,
为了拍摄最濒危的淡水河豚
the Planet Earth team joined the world's leading expert - Uzma Khan.
「地球脉动」摄制组与世界顶尖专家乌兹玛·汗展开合作
The first time I saw Indus dolphin, I was just amazed.
我第一次见到印度河豚时 简直惊呆了
It's a beautiful creature, you know,
它是一种美丽的生物
it's like love at first sight. It's so unique.
我对它一见钟情 它太独特了
Uzma has been studying the last remaining population for over 20 years.
20年来 乌兹玛一直在研究印度河豚的种群数量
There's a dolphin that surfaced just right there.
那里有一只印度河豚冒出水面
Indus river dolphin can only live in freshwater.
印度河豚只能存活于淡水中
It is only found in Pakistan and nowhere else.
只分布于巴基斯坦
And we only have about 2,000 of them left in the Indus River.
印度河中只剩下约2000只了
So, you know, each individual is special.
每一只印度河豚都弥足珍贵
Following the dolphins in the murky water is extremely challenging.
在浑浊的水中跟随印度河豚十分困难
They only surface for a split second
它们跃出水面的瞬间稍纵即逝
and that makes protecting them difficult, too.
这也使得保护它们变得困难
Their greatest threat is becoming trapped in the irrigation canals.
对它们最大的威胁是会被困在灌溉渠里
But Uzma may have a solution,
但乌兹玛也许有一种解决方案
and teams up with a rescue unit...
她与救援队展开合作
..to attempt something never done before.
以尝试一些新东西
This is the first time we'll be putting satellite tags
这是我们第一次在亚洲的河豚上
on river dolphins in Asia.
设置卫星标记
Sensors has not been tested on this species,
传感器还没有进行过这类物种的测试
there's a little bit of anxiety, but if they work,
虽然有点担心 但如果运行顺利
then it's going to be a breakthrough for conservation.
那么这将是物种保护工作的一个突破
Uzma has been developing a suitable tag for over ten years
十数年来 乌兹玛一直在开发一种合适的标记
and hopes it will help her collect critical data
希望这能帮助她收集
on how the dolphins are moving through the dams and canals.
河豚如何跨越水坝和运河的关键数据
But in order to tag, she will first need a successful rescue.
但为了能够标记河豚 必须先有河豚得到救援
This is the plan for ou rescue today.
这是我们今天的救援计划
I'm usually very concerned when a rescue is happening.
每次救援时 我都很担心
Don't let water get in the blowhole
别让水进到呼吸孔里
and don't squeeze too tight.
也别挤压河豚
You know, the divers, they are very experienced,
潜水员实际上经验丰富
but a part of me is always very worried.
但我总是会有些担心
They are wild animals that have never been handled.
它们是人类从未应对过的野生动物
It's really quite a risky thing that they're undertaking here.
救援队这项工作真的很冒险
There's a good chance the dolphin might die.
河豚很有可能活不下来
But, of course, they're balancing that against the fact
但如果不尝试救援
that they definitely will die if they stay in here,
它们一定会死
so it's a risk they have to take.
所以必须冒这个险
Have they got the dolphin? Yeah, I think so. They've got it.
-他们救起河豚了吗 -是的 救起来了
Now speed is key.
现在是生死时速
We're now bombing across the field on the way to the release site,
我们现在正全速赶往放生地点
and I think Uzma went ahead of us, so I'm really hopeful
我认为乌兹玛在我们前头
that she'll get her opportunity to tag the dolphin.
希望她能有机会设下标记
But rescue missions don't always go to plan.
但救援任务有时也会偏离轨迹
What happened?
怎么回事
A puncture.
轮胎被扎破了
Hey, come here! Grab the mattress!
过来 抬起床垫
The dolphin is quickly moved to the film crew's truck.
河豚被快速转移到摄制组的车上
Bring the water tank!
把水箱拿过来
Put it further forward.
把它放在更里面点
But with no roof for shelter,
但由于没有遮蔽物
the dolphin is at greater risk of dehydration.
河豚脱水而死的风险更高了
The stakes are high, even right now.
哪怕是现在 风险也很高
It's a cute little animal and we don't want it to die.
这是一只可爱的小动物 我们不希望它失去生命
Slow, slow, slow.
慢点慢点
The team re-route to the closest release site.
团队改道前往距离最近的放生地点
There can be no more delay.
不能再拖了
Uzma calls off the tagging.
乌兹玛取消了标记计划
It's unfortunate because we were all prepared,
这很不幸 因为我们已经做好了准备
we were very excited since morning, all geared up,
一大早我们就准备就绪 非常兴奋
but hopefully we'll get an opportunity to tag the next rescue.
希望下次救援行动能有机会设置标记
A few days later, Uzma finally gets her chance.
几天后 乌兹玛终于等到了机会
It's a very exciting day for us.
很激动的一天
It's OK.
好了
The moment that we have been waiting for, over ten years.
这一刻我们等待了十多年
Just stay calm.
冷静下来
OK, it's good to go.
好了 可以了
Congratulations.
恭喜
Well done.
干得好
I am very happy, very happy.
我很高兴 特别高兴
I think it's a great accomplishment.
我认为这是个了不起的成就
It's the happiest moment of my life.
这是我人生中最高兴的一刻
Within a few weeks, the tags begin to reveal some new insights.
几周中 标记开始帮助我们能更多的了解印度河豚
They are moving quite a lot, which we never expected.
它们移动的很频繁 这是我们从未预料到的
So one of the dolphins actually went about 46km upstream
一只河豚从放生处逆流而上46公里之远
from the release site, and the other thing is that we thought
还有一个新发现就是
that they will stay in the main river stream,
我们本以为河豚会留在河流干流
but they are using side channels. It is extremely interesting.
但实际上它们经常会游进支流中 特别有意思
Tracking the movement of the tagged dolphins
追踪受标记河豚的动向
will help Uzma better understand
将帮助乌兹玛更好的了解
when and where they become trapped...
它们被困的时间与地点
..helping safeguard the future of this most endangered animal.
这将帮助保护这种濒危动物未来的生存
Next time...
下一集
..forests.
茂密的森林
A hidden world...
一片隐蔽的世界
..where lives are intimately entwined...
在这里 生命以出人意料的方式
..in the most unexpected ways.
紧密地交织在一起
Habitat Explorer brings animals and their habitats to life.
「栖息地探索者」生动地展现动物和它们的栖息地
Explore this free interactive and make origami animals.
探索这个免费互动程序并制作折纸动物
Go to bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
前往bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
and follow the links to the Open University.
点击链接进入开放大学
Or to order a free printed version,
或者订购免费印刷版
visit the website or call the number on the screen.
欢迎访问网站或拨打屏幕上的号码